"My Air Jordans cost a hundred with tax.
حذائي (اير جوردان) يكلف 100 بالضرائب
My suede Starters jacket says Raiders on the back.
سترتي (ستارترس) السويدية مكتوب عليها غزاة (Raiders) بالخلف
I'm stylin', smilin', lookin' real mean,
انا البس الموضة. ابتسم و ابدو لئيم حقاً
because it ain't about being heard, just being seen.
لأنه ليس ان تكون مسموعاًفقط ان تكون تحت نظر الجميع
My leather Adidas baseball cap matches
قبعتي (adidas) الجلدية تماثل
my fake Gucci backpack. (Laughter)
حقيبة ظهر (gucci) المقلدة (ضحك)
Ain't nobody who looks as good as me,
لا يوجد من هو افضل مني شكلاً
but this costs money, it sure ain't free,
لكن هذا يكلف المالانا متأكد انه ليس مجاني
and I gots no job, no money at all,
و ليس لدي عملليس لدي مال على الاطلاق
but it's easy to steal all this from the mall.
لكنه من السهل ان تسرق كل هذا من مجمع التسوق.
Parents say I shouldn't, but I knows I should.
الاباء يقولون انه لا ينبغي علي فعل ذلكلكني اعرف انه ينبغي.
Got to do what I can to make sure I look good,
يجب ان اعمل ما استطيع لأكون متأكداً ان ابدو حسن الشكل.
and the reason I have to look real good, well, to tell you the truth, man,
و السبب في انه يجب علي ان ابدو بصورة جيدةحسناً. لأقل لك الحقيقة يا رجل
I don't know why. Guess it makes me feel special inside.
لا ادري لماذا. اخمن انه يجعلني اشعر بالتميز في الداخل
When I'm wearing fresh gear I don't have to hide,
عندما ارتدي ملابس جديدة لا يجب ان اختبئ
and I really must get some new gear soon
و يجب ان احضر ملابس جديدة قريباً
or my ego will pop like a 10-cent balloon.
او سيتفجر غروري كبالون بقيمة 10 سنت.
But security is tight at all the shops. Every day there are more and more cops.
لكن الاجرائات الامنية مشددة لكل المحلات.كل يوم هنالك المزيد و المزيد من الشرطيين
My crew is laughing at me because I'm wearing old gear.
شلتي تضحك علي لأنني البس ملابس ليست على الموضة.
School's almost over. Summer is near.
اقتربت المدرسة على الانتهاءاقترب الصيف
And I'm sportin' torn Jordans.
و حزاء (Jordan) اهترأ
I need something new. Only one thing left to do.
احتاج لشيئ جديدلم يتبقى لي الا ان افعل شيئ واحد.
Cut school Friday, catch the subway downtown,
اتغيب عن المدرسة في الجمعةالحق بالمترو الى وسط المدينة
check out my victims hangin' around.
اراقب ضحيتي و هو يتسكع
Maybe I'll get lucky and find easy prey.
ربما سأكون محظوظاً واجد ضحية سهلة
Got to get some new gear. There's no other way.
يجب ان امتلك ملابس جديدة. لا توجد طريقة اخرى
I'm ready and willing. I'm packing my gun.
انا جاهز و على استعداد. و مسدسي معبأ
This is serious business. This ain't no fun.
هذا عمل جاد. انه ليس بتسلية
And I can't have my posse laughin' at me.
و لن اتحمل ان يضحك علي
I'mma cop something dope, just wait, you'll see.
سأتي بشيئ عجيب. انتظر سترى
Come out of the station, West 4th near the park,
اخرج من المحطة غرب الرابعة بالقرب من المنتزه
brothers shooting hoops and someone remarks,
اصدقائي يلعبون و حينها يلاحظ احدهم
'Hey homes, where you get them Nik's?'
يا صديقي من اين اتيت بهذا ال (Nik's)؟
I says to myself, 'Yeah. I likes 'em, I likes.'
اقول لنفسي: نعم يعجبونني
They were Q-tip white, bright and blinding my eyes.
كان لونهم ابيض ب(Q tip) يلمعون و يعمون عيناي.
The red emblem of Michael looked as if it could fly.
الشعار الاحمر لمايكل يبدو و كأنه يمكنه ان يطير
Not one spot of dirt. The Airs were brand new.
بدون بقعة واحدة من الاوساخ. الحزاء كان جديداً
Had my pistol and knew just what to do.
معي مسدسي و اعرف فقط ماذا سأفعل.
Waited until it was just the right time, followed him very closely behind.
انتظرت حتى الوقت المناسب. لحقت به
He made a left turn on Houston, I pulled out my gun,
اخذ بيساره عند Houston. اخرجت مسدسي
and I said, 'Gimme them Jordans!'
و قلت: اعطني حزاء ال Jordan
And the punk tried to run.
و الفاسق حاول الهروب
Took off fast, didn't get far. I fired,'Pow!'
جرى بسرعة. لم يصل بعيداً. اطلقت عياراً "باو!"
Fool fell between two parked cars.
المغفل وقع بين عربتين واقفتين
He was coughing, crying, blood spilled on the street.
كان يسعل. يبكي. الدماء متدفقة في الشارع.
And I snatched them Air Jordans off of his feet.
انتزعت ذاك الحزاء من رجليه
While laying there dying, all he could say
و حين كان يرقد على الارض و هو يموت. كل ما قاله:
was, "Please man, don't take my Air Jordans away."
ارجوك. لا تأخذ حزائي Air Jordans مني.
You'd think he'd be worried about staying alive.
قد تظن انه سيكون قلقاً على حياته.
As I took off with his sneakers, there was tears in his eyes.
عندما انتزعت الحزاء من رجلي. كانت هناك دموعاً في عيناه.
Very next day, I bopped into school
في اليوم التالي طهرت في المدرسة
with my brand new Air Jordans, man, I was cool.
بحزائي الجديد. لقد كنت حسن الشكل.
I killed to get 'em, but hey, I don't care,
لقد قتلت لأحصل عليهم. لكنني لا اهتم
because now I needs a new jacket to wear."
لأنه الان احتاج لسترة جديدة"
Thank you. (Applause)
شكراً لكم (تصفيق)
For the last 15 years that I have been performing,
في ال15 سنة الماضية التي كنت اؤدي
all I ever wanted to do was transcend poetry to the world.
كل ما اردته هو ان انشر الشعر للعالم
See, it wasn't enough for me to write a book.
لم يكن بالكافي لي ان اكتب كتاباً
It wasn't enough for me to join a slam competition,
لم يكن من الكافي ان انضم الى مسابقة نقدية
and while those things hold weight,
و حين كانت تلك الاشياء كافية
it wasn't the driving force that pushes the pen to the pad.
لم تكن القوة المحركة التي تدفعني للكتابة
The hunger and thirst was, and still remains:
الجوع و العطش كان و لا يزال باقي
How do I get people who hate poetry
كيف يمكنني ان اجعل الناس الذين يكرهون الشعر
to love me?
ان يحبونني
Because I'm an extension of my work,
لأنني انا امتداد لعملي
and if they love me, then they will love my work,
اذا احبونني. سيحبون عملي
and if they love my work, then they will love poetry,
اذا احبوا عملي اذاً سيحبون الشعر
and if they love poetry, then I will have done my job,
اذا احبوا الشعرعندها لقد اتممت مهمتي
which is to transcend it to the world.
و هي ان انشر الشعر للعالم
And in 1996, I found the answer in principles
و في 1996. وجدت الجواب في المبادئ
in a master spoken-word artist named Reg E. Gaines,
عند فنان في الspoken word اسمه ريج اي. قاينز
who wrote the famous poem, "Please Don't Take My Air Jordans."
الذي كتب القصيدة المشهورة "ارجوك لا تأخذ حزائي Air Jordans "
And I followed this guy everywhere until I had him in the room,
لحقت به في كل مكان حتى اصبحنا في مكان واحد
and I read him one of my pieces,
و قرأت له احدى قصائدي.
and you know what he told me?
و هل تعلمون ماذا قال لي؟
"Yo' wack.
ايها العبيط
You know what the problem is with you, homie?
هل تعرف مشكلتك يا هومي؟
You don't read other people's poetry,
انت لا تقرأ اعمال الاخرين
and you don't got any subordination for verbal measures
و ليس لديك اي تبعية في التدابير اللفظية
to tonal consideration." (Laughter)
للنظر النغمي.(ضحك)
Now he kept on rambling
و قد واصل في كلامه غير المفهوم
about poetry and styles and Nuyorican Friday nights.
عن الشعر و عن اساليبه و عن ليلات الجمعة النيوريكانية
Now I could have quit. I should have quit.
الان كان بإمكاني ان اصمتكان يجب ان اصمت
I mean, I thought poetry was just self-expression.
اعني. لقد ظننت ان الشعر هو فقط طريقة للتعبير
I didn't know you actually have to have creative control.
لم ادري انه يجب ان تستطيع ان تتحكم في الابداع
So instead of quitting, I followed him everywhere.
هكذا بدلاً من ان اصمتلحقت به في كل مكان
When he was writing a Broadway show, I would be outside of the door.
عندما كان يكتب عرض لبرودوايعندها انتظر خارج الباب
I would wake him up at, like, 6:30 in the morning
اوقظه عند 6:30 في الصباح
to ask him who's the best poet.
لاسأله من هو افضل شاعر
I remember eating the eyes of a fish right out of the sea
اتذكر انني اكلت عينا سمكة خارجة لتوها من البحر
because he told me it was brain food.
لأني قال لي انه غذاء للعقل
Then one day I told him,
في يوم من الايام قلت له
"Reg E., what is subordination for verbal measures to tonal consideration?" (Laughter)
ريج اي. ما هي التبعية في التدابير اللفظية للنظر النغمي؟(ضحك)
And he handed me a black-and-white printed out thesis
قدم لي اطروحة مطبوعة بالاسود و الابيض
on a poet named Etheridge Knight
لقصيدة اسمها ايثريدج نايت
and the oral nature of poetry,
و الطبيعة النطقية للقصيدة
and from that point,
من تلك النقطة
Reggie stopped becoming the best to me,
لم يعد ريجي الافضل بالنسبة لي
because what Etheridge Knight taught me
لأن ما علمه لي ايثريدج نايت
was that I could make my words sound like music,
انه يمكنني ان اجعل كلماتي كالموسيقى
even my small ones, the monosyllables,
حتى الصغيرة احادية اللفظ
the ifs, ands, buts, whats,
(ifs. ands . buts. whats )
the gangsta in my slang could fall right on the ear,
حتى العصابية في لهجتي العامية يمكن ان تسمع بطريقة اسلس
and from then on, I started chasing Etheridge Knight.
و من عندها بدأت بملاحقة ايثريدج نايت
I wanted to know which poet he read,
اردت ان اعرف اي قصيدة قرأ
and I landed on a poem called ["Dark Prophecy: Sing of Shine"],
و وجدت قصيدة اسمها (Darl Prophecy: Sing of Shine )
a toast signifying that got me on the biggest stage
نخب يدل. ارسلني الى اكبر مسرح
a poet could ever be:
ما يمكن للقصيدة:
Broadway, baby.
برودواي يا حبيبي
And from that point, I learned how to pull the mic away
و من تلك اللحظة تعلمت كيف ابعد المايكروفون
and attack the poetry with my body.
و اهجم على الشعر بجسدي
But that wasn't the biggest lesson I ever learned.
لكنه لم يكن اكبر درس تعلمته
The biggest lesson I learned was many years later
اكبر درس تعلمته كان بعد عدة سنوات
when I went to Beverly Hills and I ran into a talent agent
عندما ذهبت الى بيفيرلي هيلز. و التقيت عميل موهوب
who looked at me up and down
الذي نظر الي من فوق الى تحت
and said I don't look like I have any experience
و قال انه لا يبدو انني لدي اي خبرة
to be working in this business.
لأعمل في هذا المجال
And I said to him, "Listen, punk fool,
و قلت له: اسمع ايها العبيط الاهبل
you're a failed actor who became an agent,
انت ممثل فاشل الذي اصبح عميل
and you know why you failed as an actor?
و هل تعرف لماذا فشلت كممثل؟
Because people like me took your job.
لأن الناس امثالي اخذوا وظيفتك
I've traveled all the way from Cleveland and Essex
لقد اتيت من كليفلاند و اسيكس
in East New York, took the local 6 line up to the hookers of Hunt's Point
في شرق نيويورك.اخذ من المحليين 6 طوابير الى مومسات Hunt's point
who were in my way on my way to master the art of space,
الذين كانوا في طريقي لأتقن فن الفراغ
and the one-to-infinite amount of man, woman and child
و عددية الرجال و النساء و الاطفال من واحد الى ما لا نهاية
you can fit in there only so I can push them
يمكنك وضعهم هناك فقط لأدفعهم
to the back of the wall with my experience.
الى الحائط الخلفي بخبرتي
People have bought tickets to my experience
الناس اشتروا تذاكر لخبرتي
and used them as refrigerator magnets to let them know
و علقوهم في الثلاجة فقط لتذكرهم
that the revolution is near, so stock up.
ان الثورة قريبة حتى يحضروا مخزونهم
I'm so experienced that when you went
انني متمرس بشدة لدرجة انه عندما تذهب الى
to a privileged school to learn a Shakespearean sonnet,
مدرسة متميزة للتعلم السوناتا الشكسبيرية
I was getting those beats kicked and shoved into me.
كانت تلك النغمات ترمى و تحشر الى داخلي
I can master shock of "The Crying Game" with the awe
يمكنني ان احترف (the crying game) برعب
of a child being called an AIDS victim by a bully who didn't know
طفل الذي ينادى بضخية الايدز بمتنمر لم يعرف
that it was his father who gave it to my mother,
ان اباه اعطاه لأمه
and that's a double entendre.
و ذلك الم مضاعف
I'm so experienced that when you went to the Fell School
انني خبير بشدة حيث انك عندما ذهبت لمدرسة فيل
and all the rich little fairy boys decided to sponsor a child
و كل الاولاد الاغنياء الرقيقين قرروا ان يدعموا طفلاً
in it, that was me, but kicked me out when I was caught
كان انا. لكنهم طردوني عندما قبضت
teaching the fairy boys how to rob the PATS off a pair of Lee Jeans
اعلم الاولاد الرقيقين كيف ترق بنطلون جينز من PATS
and bring them to VIM. Let me see Chekhov pull that off.
و احضاره الى VIMدعني ارى ان كان يمقدور Chekhov ان يفعل هذا
Sanford Meisner was my Uncle Artie yelling silently to himself,
Sanford Meisner كان عمي ارتي يصرخ بصمت لنفسه:
"Something's always wrong when nothing's always right."
دائماً هنالك شيئ خاطئ عندما لا يوجد شيئ دائماً صحيح
Method acting is nothing but a mixture
طريقة التمثيل ليست سوى خليط
of multiple personalities, believing your own lies are reality,
من شخصيات متعددة تؤمن بأن كذباتك هي حقيقة
like in high school cool Kenny telling me he wanted to be a cop.
كما في المدرسة الثانوية كيني الظريف يقول لي انه يريد ان يصبح شرطي
Dude, you go to Riker's Island Academy.
انت ملتحق ب بأكادمية Riker Island
I could make David Mamet
استطيع ان اجعل ديفيد ماميت
psychoanalyze my attack on dialogue,
يحلل هجمتي من حواري
Stanislavski be as if he were Bruce Lee
ستينسلافسكي كما يكون بروس لي
kicking your roster of talentless students up and down Crenshaw.
يرمي بلائحة الطلبة غير الموهوبين فوق و تحت Crenshaw
So what, your actors studied guerrilla theater at the London Rep?
اذن لماذا. ممثلينك درسوا Guerrilla theater في London Rep؟
Let me tell you an ancient Chinese Saturday afternoon
دعني احكي لك عن سر كونغ فو ظهيرة السبت
kung fu secret.
لصينين قدماء
Boards don't hit back.
الالواح لا ترد الضربة
You think black entertainers have it hard finding work
قد تظن ان المسليين السود يلاقون صعوبة في ايجاد عمل
in this business? I'm a suspicious mulatto,
في هذا المجال؟ انا اسمر مشبوه
which means I'm too black to be white and too white to be doing it right.
ما يعني انني ايضاً اسود و اكون ابيض ايضاً و اعمل ذلك بطريقة صحيحة
Forget the American ghetto. I've cracked stages in Soweto,
انسى الغيتو الامريكية. لقد هزمت مسارح في Soweto
buried abortion babies in potter's field and still managed to keep a smile on my face,
اطفال مجهضون مدفونون في Potter's field و لا ازال استطيع وضع ابتسامة على وجهي
so whatever you curse at me to your caddyshack
اذن اياً ما تلعنه لوجهي لكاديشاكك
go-for-this, go-for-that assistant when I walk out that door,
اذهب لهذا. اذهب لذاك المساعد عندما اخرج من ذاك الباب
whatever slander you send my way,
اي افتراء ترسله لي
your mother.
امك
Thank you. (Applause)
شكراً لكم(تصفيق)